[SPEAKER_00]: So, in this sutta, Majjhima Nikāya 78, the Buddha is discussing the view of a certain ascetic, who basically says...
[SPEAKER_00]: This was his statement.
[SPEAKER_00]: Carpenter, when a man possesses four qualities, I describe him as accomplished in what is wholesome, perfected in what is wholesome, an ascetic invincible attained to the supreme attainment.
[SPEAKER_00]: What are the four?
[SPEAKER_00]: Here, he does no evil bodily actions, he utters no evil speech, he has no evil intentions, and he does not make his living by any evil livelihood.
[SPEAKER_00]: When a man possesses these four qualities, I describe him as accomplished in what is wholesome, perfected in what is wholesome, as an ascetic, invincible, attained to the supreme attainment.
[SPEAKER_00]: That was the statement of this ascetic, and then the Buddha replied to it with
[SPEAKER_00]: If that were so, then, a young, tender infant, lying prone, is accomplished in what is wholesome, perfected in what is wholesome, an ascetic, invincible, attained to the supreme attainment, according to the wanderer, Ughamana's statement.
[SPEAKER_00]: For a young, tender infant, lying prone, does not even have the notion body, so how should he do an evil bodily action beyond mere riddling?
[SPEAKER_00]: a young tender infant lying prone does not even have the notion speech so how should he utter evil speech beyond mere whining a young tender infant lying prone does not even have the notion intention so how should he have evil intentions beyond beyond mere sulking a young young tender infant lying prone does not even have the notion livelihood
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the Buddha is basically refuting here the idea that just because you don't do stuff externally, that doesn't mean that
[SPEAKER_00]: You are already accomplished and wholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, further on, he says... What are unwholesome...
[SPEAKER_00]: He goes on to define what are the actual unwholesome habits.
[SPEAKER_00]: And he says, they are unwholesome bodily actions, unwholesome verbal actions, and evil livelihood.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then, he describes, what do these unwholesome habits originate from?
[SPEAKER_00]: And he says, they should be said to originate from mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: What mind?
[SPEAKER_00]: Though mind is multiple, varied, and of different aspects, there is mind affected by lust, by aversion, and by muddledness, or delusion.
[SPEAKER_00]: Unwholesome habits originate from this.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, how does he define wholesome habits?
[SPEAKER_00]: He says, they should also be said to originate from mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Though mind is multiple, varied, and of different aspects, there is mind not affected by lust, by aversion, or by delusion.
[SPEAKER_00]: Wholesome habits originate from this.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the idea here is that, even though a person might not be
[SPEAKER_00]: Outwardly performing any of the unwholesome actions, like that tender infant, for example, wholesomeness doesn't depend on that.
[SPEAKER_02]: It depends on the mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that tender infant, even though he's not doing anything, his mind has the underlying tendency to lust, aversion, and delusion, even though it's not being outwardly expressed in these coarse ways.
[SPEAKER_02]: So,
[SPEAKER_02]: That leads us then to the point of what is wholesome and unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, can a person... because, you know, we talk about undertaking the virtue, the sense restraint and that sort of thing, but it's easy to then think that wholesomeness isn't just doing this, undertaking this behavior, as opposed to whatever you used to be doing before.
[SPEAKER_02]: So,
[SPEAKER_02]: How can you know, then, that your behavior is not just emulating the behavior of an arahant, but is actually matching it on that level that matters, that it's actually developing your mind?
[SPEAKER_02]: Because that's what wholesome is.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, how can you know whether your actions by body, speech and mind are wholesome?
[SPEAKER_02]: Can you just follow a prescribed set of rules or observances defined by someone, even the Buddha himself?
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, would following, for example, the whole vinaya, in its entirety, to its perfection, ensure that you are committing wholesome and avoiding unwholesome?
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't guarantee that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, how... but how then could you tell?
[SPEAKER_02]: I am doing something unwholesome now.
[SPEAKER_02]: Let's say you avoided the coarse stuff by undertaking the eight precepts.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, within that, what is unwholesome then, apart from the obvious actions that you're not doing anymore?
[SPEAKER_02]: Is it that, for example, studying dhamma or meditating is automatically wholesome?
[SPEAKER_02]: Because it's about them.
[SPEAKER_01]: Uh-huh.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, that doesn't follow either.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And also, these eight precepts, you know, about not killing, not stealing, not taking toxicants and so on, that is on the level of behavior,
[SPEAKER_01]: That can be seen even from the outside.
[SPEAKER_01]: But whether something is wholesome or unwholesome has to do with that very basis or mind that gives rise to wholesome or unwholesome actions.
[SPEAKER_01]: And essentially, it has to do with the intentions based on which one is acting.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that is, let's say, a dimension beyond
[SPEAKER_01]: And what is that why, more specifically?
[SPEAKER_01]: Is it... Like, if I ask you, why are you doing this?
[SPEAKER_02]: And then the answer you give me is that... Like, let's say I ask you why are you doing this, and you give me a satisfactory answer.
[SPEAKER_03]: Does that mean it's wholesome?
[SPEAKER_01]: No, because somebody can still...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, reasons and arguments here could still be like, well, the weather was nice, so I decided to do it, or... which might be a reason, but that is not where the intentions are.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, for example,
[SPEAKER_01]: If one is acting out of one of the five hindrances, that would be unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just to give an indication.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, more generally, greed, hatred and delusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: To the extent that one has understood greed, hatred and delusion, one should refrain from acting out of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it would depend on understanding those things and keeping them in mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, then, does... do those five hindrances have specific places where they arise?
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, only here, I'm going to experience this?
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, eh, specific... only... would they arise only in specific contexts?
[SPEAKER_01]: Would the five hindrances only arise in specific contexts?
[SPEAKER_04]: What do you mean by arise, in this case?
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, taking the hindrances not as instances of acting out, but as the underlying tendency?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, just colloquially speaking, or you could take it as greed, aversion, and delusion.
[SPEAKER_02]: Is it something that only comes up in specific instances or specific situations?
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, I guess, I mean...
[SPEAKER_04]: It's an underlying tendency, so maybe the obvious kind of indications that they're present might only come up from time to time, but the fact that they were able to come up indicates that, yeah, the tendency was there.
[SPEAKER_04]: Though that's kind of just repeating what we said.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, like, the point I'm trying to make is that, obviously, there will be things that are more strongly bound up with those hindrances.
[SPEAKER_02]: But fundamentally, or with the defilements in general, but fundamentally those things...
[SPEAKER_02]: form like the background of your experience in any situation.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that means that there is nothing that you can rest assured that this is not unwholesome, that this won't be underlied by one of these unwholesome intentions.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like that, like that's why I mentioned dhamma, for example.
[SPEAKER_02]: Many people might not necessarily realize that things like, you know,
[SPEAKER_02]: Studying dhamma, or meditating, or making effort to it to practice, can be underlied by those same intentions, which means, by those same unwholesome intentions of
[SPEAKER_02]: Longing, aversion, indolence, restlessness, anxiety, doubt.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's what makes it unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not because, like, this is about dhamma and this other thing is about mundane stuff.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then, this is wholesome and this is unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's anything that is underlined by that mental state.
[SPEAKER_02]: Anything that is underlined by a mind that
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that means that, eh...
[SPEAKER_02]: Even the intention that you might state as, I'm doing this because of such and such, like you said, because the weather is nice or something, even that would be underlined, underlain by that level of a hindrance, by the level of your mind pulling you towards something and you giving in to that.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's what makes it... it doesn't matter what... it might even be like, I don't know,
[SPEAKER_02]: Doing something that the Buddha himself told you to do, or like the most wholesome kind of activity you could imagine, even then, you would be increasing, you would be going in the direction of unwholesome, if your mind at that time is underlain by these states, and you're proliferating them.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that means that then,
[SPEAKER_02]: The kind of carefulness that has to be employed is not on the level of the usual.
[SPEAKER_02]: You know, when monks would really try really hard to protect the vinaya, for example, it would be kind of directed
[SPEAKER_03]: Almost outwardly, like the external properties of how I do this, when I do it, like what... in what condition this is appropriate, in what condition is it not appropriate.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, basically, all that means is that you would never be able to be free from doubt.
[SPEAKER_02]: In regard to your own virtue, and in regard to your wholesomeness and unwholesomeness, because somebody else may come along and say, no, no, that in that context, you shouldn't have done this, you should have done something else.
[SPEAKER_02]: So then, at any point, that could be undermined by something that you didn't know.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, if virtue depended on, like, making the right choice in that external sense, at any point, like, it could be proven... what you did could be proven wrong.
[SPEAKER_02]: But if it always depends only on your state of mind, then the whole world can come and tell you you made a mistake, and you know that that's not the case.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, it's a mistake in a worldly sense, sure, but in the sense of acting out of craving, you would be able to 100%
[SPEAKER_02]: With 100% certainty, say, no, I did not act out of craving.
[SPEAKER_02]: I did not commit an offense in the context of dhamma.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's what the kind of accomplishment and virtue that a person should develop.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's really what extreme entry is.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's the ability to have that perfect certainty of wholesome and unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_02]: And most importantly, regard to virtue.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because your virtue doesn't depend anymore on the
[SPEAKER_02]: Things that, on the world, or on anything that was predefined, it doesn't even depend on your information that you gained from the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like the rules that you learned, or the habits that you developed.
[SPEAKER_02]: It depends only on knowing.
[SPEAKER_02]: What is your state of mind?
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, not acting out of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, even the consequence, even the worldly consequences of those actions, they might turn out to be somewhat unfortunate.
[SPEAKER_01]: And people might criticize someone for that.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, that is then understood as, okay, that's unfortunate.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that, that is not what constitutes a fault in terms of dhamma.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then, yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: You, you...
[SPEAKER_02]: It's basically essential to abandon the view that good actions will result in happiness.
[SPEAKER_02]: In that immediate sense, like, if I do something good, it should, you know, result in good consequences because, well, if you don't have the right view, you don't know what the right type of happiness is to begin with.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, the happiness that you would expect to come from your actions is still going to be on the external level, like you would expect, you know, pain not to come to you.
[SPEAKER_02]: But really, the happiness that necessarily comes from virtue is the happiness of
[SPEAKER_02]: Not being bothered, even if bad things happen.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's a different thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the blamelessness of the accomplishment of virtue.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, eh... Can I ask a question?
[SPEAKER_04]: Maybe it's a little bit like a step back, but just to clarify.
[SPEAKER_04]: Let's say, like, someone just learned about the eight precepts, respect them, like, he's practicing sense restraint, and then he's, like, learning about the dharma, and he tries his best to go in that direction.
[SPEAKER_04]: And then, he's also asking this question, like, why am I doing that?
[SPEAKER_04]: But then, like, the answer is not, like, so clear for him, like, about is it wholesome or is it unwholesome?
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, even if he's asking himself, like, generally, like, is it, like, actually wholesome what I'm doing?
[SPEAKER_04]: He's not, like, 100% sure.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, is there is a way to actually be sure that what he's doing is wholesome or is it unwholesome?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, well, the only way to be sure would be to see the signs of the mind, which is basically the kind of... it's inextricably linked with the right view.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, being able to see the domain of your mind where greed, aversion and delusion is.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, being able to see that clearly would mean that
[SPEAKER_03]: Nobody can tell you...
[SPEAKER_03]: It works both ways.
[SPEAKER_03]: Nobody can tell you that what you did was unwholesome when it was wholesome.
[SPEAKER_03]: At the same time, when you're doing something unwholesome, you wouldn't need any sort of external confirmation or somebody else to tell you, yes, it was unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_02]: You would know for yourself.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, the doubt that a person might have is not because, like, they haven't, like, learned enough in that kind of external sense or they haven't, like,
[SPEAKER_02]: gained enough experience or something like that.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's more like, in their own mind, there is this, eh... they have not developed the discernment of that domain, even though it's already there.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, it's not like greed, aversion, delusion is not there, if you're not thinking about it.
[SPEAKER_03]: It is there.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's just that, until a person gains that that discernment, then,
[SPEAKER_03]: Everywhere, everywhere that they might be looking, won't be that place where your original delusion is.
[SPEAKER_03]: So then, that's why they would experience doubt.
[SPEAKER_02]: And the doubt would be there because, still, on some subtle level, they would still expect, like, the
[SPEAKER_02]: Confirmation to be as given by an external set of rules or relations between things.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, was this thing...
[SPEAKER_02]: In a worldly sense, let's put it this way.
[SPEAKER_02]: Let's say you
[SPEAKER_02]: You dropped a rock from a cliff and then it killed someone, accidentally.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's one of the examples we were discussing recently.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then you would have doubt, like, oh, but I shouldn't have done that because... And then, that would only happen if you thought, if you kind of
[SPEAKER_03]: Overlooked or weren't 100% sure about the fact that the only thing that mattered was the state of mind that you had at that time.
[SPEAKER_02]: Why did you throw the rock?
[SPEAKER_02]: Did you do it because you were careless?
[SPEAKER_02]: Did you do it because you were angry?
[SPEAKER_02]: Did you do it because... or some other reason?
[SPEAKER_03]: And then, if it was out of carelessness, if it was out of anger, there would be no room for doubt, because you don't know what I did was wrong.
[SPEAKER_02]: Whether the person died or not.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because, see, that wouldn't be what determined the action as unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_02]: It was the mental state that you had when you threw the rock.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, then, yeah, doubt would not apply.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, if you knew, no, I threw the rock because, I don't know, it was blocking the way and I was genuinely just trying to cross that path, then,
[SPEAKER_02]: Even if your mind would try to convince you and try to haunt you with guilt, like, no, I shouldn't have done that, I shouldn't have done that, you would know, nope, I did that out of an intention that was not unwholesome, and then, if my mind is trying to make me feel guilt, that's just a hindrance, and I know that I shouldn't give in to that, because then, basically, like, if you'd have to worry about how your mind will react to things,
[SPEAKER_02]: Then, if you use that as a measure of what's wholesome and unwholesome, then, I mean, the mind is going to feel uncomfortable with non-greed, non-aversion, non-delusion by nature, and it's going to try to trick you to
[SPEAKER_02]: Either do more than is necessary or do less than is necessary.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you can't even trust your own mind to be responding nicely when you avoid unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you could think of it as like, if you have a child,
[SPEAKER_02]: And, you know, the child might be throwing tantrums every now and then.
[SPEAKER_02]: And your goal is to teach that child not to do that, to behave properly.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, the problem is not when you let the... like, the problem is not that the child wants to go to the park, for example.
[SPEAKER_02]: The problem is that the child is throwing a tantrum for you to let him go to the park.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, in this case, putting aside the eight precepts, of course, because doing that automatically, whether you like it or not, is going to involve an unwholesome state of mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: But for everything else,
[SPEAKER_02]: What matters is, is my mind throwing a tantra on account of this?
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, to let me do it.
[SPEAKER_02]: If I do give in, I am feeding and promoting that bad habit of the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: You mean if the parent throws a tantra on benedict's altars?
[SPEAKER_01]: No, no.
[SPEAKER_03]: If a child throws a tantrum, and then the parent lets him have what he wants.
[SPEAKER_03]: Oh, I see.
[SPEAKER_03]: As a result of the tantrum.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, the child is the mind, and you are the parent, let's say.
[SPEAKER_03]: Okay, I see.
[SPEAKER_03]: So then, that is what makes something unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's like, the tantrum that the mind was throwing, giving into that, and promoting that sort of behavior, is what's making you liable to suffering in the future, because something will come along, some situation will come along, that
[SPEAKER_03]: Either, as the First Noble Truth would say, you will be either united with what you don't like, or separated from what you like.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then, the mind will be throwing a tantrum on account of that.
[SPEAKER_03]: Why?
[SPEAKER_03]: Because in the past, whenever something similar happened, like, you let it act out, either towards pleasure or away from pain.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, in the future, when pleasure comes,
[SPEAKER_03]: That sort of habit that you've been building up is going to be greater by that much, by the amount that you've been building it.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, it's unwholesome because it's increasing your own liability to suffering, not because of some other kind of external definition of what the Buddha said unwholesome is.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's because it is making you factually and genuinely
[SPEAKER_02]: Liable to the to the habits of your own mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's what undermines your safety, basically, because the world is not in your control.
[SPEAKER_03]: Things can happen that you don't expect.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, if your mind depends on having the world be a certain way, because you have been allowing it to increase that dependency through these actions, like when pleasure comes, you need to seek it.
[SPEAKER_02]: And when pain comes, you need to run away from it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then, that's how much you will be suffering when the world keeps doing what it does.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's not the fault of the world.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's the fact that you have been training your mind to... in the opposite of the right direction.
[SPEAKER_02]: That was your being, genuinely.
[SPEAKER_02]: That is your being.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's gonna be, like, underlying your
[SPEAKER_02]: Once you have built that up, you can't even... you can't choose to get out of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: That is your reality now.
[SPEAKER_02]: You have a mind that has these habits, and then you have to undo it, kind of indirectly.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can't... you'll never be able to just lock the child up and say, no, you can't do anything anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, you can't.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, how to then undo that?
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, one finds oneself already with certain habits,
[SPEAKER_01]: And now, when it comes to realization, that's not in my welfare.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, from now on, I shouldn't give in to those habits, but they're still wise.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, well, with the same example, like, you have a child that's throwing a tantrum to go to the park, but it's not throwing a tantrum to, I don't know, have his dinner.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, he's still crying.
[SPEAKER_03]: He's still crying about the park.
[SPEAKER_03]: But if you say, no, no, now you're not going to have dinner, you're not going to have anything, you're going to lock it up in the room with dark windows and... Yeah, that will be a punishment of some sort.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's not going to be training it to really kind of get rid of that habit.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, what you have to do is recognize...
[SPEAKER_03]: Even if I choose not to do anything, that will be my choice.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, if in trying to restrain my wholesome habits, I go too far in the direction of, no, now I won't do anything.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, that's not going to be... like, you're going to be doing that out of the same kind of aversion to the situation.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, what you have to do is recognize, no, I can do everything else, except
[SPEAKER_02]: The thing that the mind is craving for.
[SPEAKER_02]: Everything else, obviously, without breaking the eight precepts.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, it becomes very clear.
[SPEAKER_02]: You don't need some specific definition of what to do.
[SPEAKER_03]: All you need to know is what you shouldn't do.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's all that matters.
[SPEAKER_03]: Don't give in to this pull, to this pressure, while it's there, and everything else you can do.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, if you have a, I don't know, sensual thoughts in your mind, for example, that doesn't mean that you need to, like, again, close everything and and and lock yourself up, or get in a concentration state, so to free yourself from that.
[SPEAKER_03]: It means you can have, you can think about anything.
[SPEAKER_03]: You can think about, you know, I don't know,
[SPEAKER_03]: What you have to do tomorrow or something.
[SPEAKER_03]: But as long as it's not fueling the same lust that's there.
[SPEAKER_03]: If you keep up with that practice, you're going to see, actually, there's always a lot of space.
[SPEAKER_03]: Whenever an unwholesome state is there, there's always a lot of space for you to do other things that are not going to be rooted in that.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's just... but in the beginning, because the mind starts out, as we said, with that habit of being absorbed in greed, aversion and delusion, then it's gonna feel like, no, no, like it's the only thing you have in your experience, that you can't do anything else.
[SPEAKER_03]: But really, there's always infinite amount of things, like, that
[SPEAKER_01]: That, on that occasion, would be sort of independent of the pressure.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, it's...
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you have to see it as, like, how can I act in... not, like, how can I stop myself from doing anything, but how can I act in a way that is parallel to the feeling that is there.
[SPEAKER_03]: Parallel, meaning you're not, kind of, like,
[SPEAKER_03]: Acting out of it, sort of out of the desire to interfere with it.
[SPEAKER_03]: But no, the feeling is there, and I'm not trying to get rid of it, the pressure, and then this action is kind of happening at the same time, without being directed at the feeling, either for or against.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you're having sensual thoughts, and then you decide to go for a walk.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, is that walk going to be making you indulge in those sensual thoughts?
[SPEAKER_03]: No.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, if you start indulging in sensual thoughts, that's not because of the walk.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's because you went for a walk and decided to give it to the sensual thoughts.
[SPEAKER_02]: And, at the same time, it's not going to be rooted in running away from it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because you're not trying to suppress them.
[SPEAKER_02]: You're not trying to kind of escape from it in that direct manner out of aversion.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you can go for a walk and then
[SPEAKER_03]: If the central thoughts persist throughout the entire walk, well, so be it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because that's your kamma.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's the habit.
[SPEAKER_03]: These things are happening because of the tendencies that you've been proliferating from before.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, yeah, you just endure it.
[SPEAKER_03]: As the Buddha said, you refrain from putting in the fuel.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, it's as if there was a fire burning, and a man would not be throwing sticks and leaves and dry leaves into it.
[SPEAKER_03]: It doesn't say, like, the man kind of, you know, takes, I don't know... Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because...
[SPEAKER_03]: That would be, again, interfering with it.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you let it burn for as long as it... for as long as it has been... for as long as the fuel is there for it to burn.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, yeah, that's the way to get...
[SPEAKER_02]: It has to go out.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's the way to get rid of things.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, eh... and that's that sutta that where the Buddha talks about, eh... the
[SPEAKER_02]: There are five ways to get rid of your thoughts, how people translate it.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's like, it says, when your mind is being overwhelmed by thoughts of desire, aversion, and delusion, it says you attend to a different sign that is connected with the wholesome, that people would think that means
[SPEAKER_02]: No, I need to attend to a different sign so as to get rid of this, kind of, the whole thing that I'm experiencing.
[SPEAKER_03]: But no, it means you just find something that isn't
[SPEAKER_02]: It's going to be rooted in trying to get rid or trying to delight in that same thing that's assailing you.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then it says, as he does that, those unwholesome states are abandoned.
[SPEAKER_03]: It doesn't say that by focusing on the different thing,
[SPEAKER_03]: That's how you immediately get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, we should clear up that abandoning an wholesome state does not mean that one is focusing on another object, because the thing in front of you that you look at is not what determines wholesome or unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the shift is in the sign, which is in the other direction, and then you could be looking at that very same thing, because the sign has now shifted.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, and also, like, it's... as we just said, it's the mental state that's the problem.
[SPEAKER_03]: So,
[SPEAKER_03]: You can't get rid of the mental state directly, because the mind is not... like, your intentions are a result of the mental state, so you can't kind of get behind it.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, what you would do is just not act.
[SPEAKER_03]: Any sign that you attend, or any thought that you attend, or any action that you do, you make it so that it's not
[SPEAKER_02]: Going with the grain of the... whatever craving is there.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then, indirectly, by not providing the fuel, those thoughts would cease.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because you're not... it's like... the Buddha described it also as... when flies are buzzing around you,
[SPEAKER_03]: That has to be because there's some kind of smell that's attracting them.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you remove the rotten meat, and they might still be kind of going around, because, like, they came... there's still some lingering smell, let's say.
[SPEAKER_03]: But, if you genuinely took away the meat,
[SPEAKER_03]: Or whatever it was.
[SPEAKER_03]: Eventually, they're gonna leave.
[SPEAKER_03]: They're off to go.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: So... but if you then concern yourself with, you know, swatting away the flies, and you're not actually removing the origin of the problem, then you're gonna maybe kill those specific flies.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, there's always gonna be more.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that is the first thing that the Buddha says, like, attends to a different sign.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, he discusses four other ways in which one can deal with these thoughts as well.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, all of them would be kind of within that first one.
[SPEAKER_03]: You find... Like, you don't even need to think of it as like, oh, I'm meditating, and then, I have my clothes, and then, I have this thought, and then, I find another thought.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's just throughout your entire life.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, I have some unwholesome state arising, and I simply make sure that I don't
[SPEAKER_03]: go in that direction, specifically.
[SPEAKER_03]: I can go everywhere else except in that direction.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then, that brings us to another point.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, the wholesome, as the sutta just defined, it said... it didn't say that the wholesomeness is the mind of
[SPEAKER_03]: You know, outwardly renouncing things, or outwardly having loving-kindness, and outwardly having wisdom.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's that the wholesome mind is the mind of non-lust, non-aversion, and non-delusion.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, it doesn't mean like, in order to not be deluded, I need to go and start reading dhamma, or start contemplating dhamma, because otherwise I'm deluded.
[SPEAKER_03]: Or, I need to give things physically, like give up my everything, all my possessions, because otherwise I have lost.
[SPEAKER_03]: Or I need to be, you know, being extra... invest extra effort in being polite to people because otherwise I'm acting out of aversion.
[SPEAKER_03]: No.
[SPEAKER_03]: It just means the absence of that unwholesome state is automatically the wholesome state.
[SPEAKER_03]: So then, you move your mind to a wholesome sign, meaning any sign that is not going to be involved with any of these three things.
[SPEAKER_03]: And again, at any time,
[SPEAKER_03]: Any unwholesome state that you have in your mind, it's always going to be something specific.
[SPEAKER_03]: You can't have, like, unwholesomeness, kind of, like, ambiguous, like, it's just there.
[SPEAKER_03]: No.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's always, it's always pushing you towards something.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then you can always avoid that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so perhaps it's worthwhile repeating that when the Buddha discusses wholesome and unwholesome, he always first says avoid the unwholesome and then develop the wholesome.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's never the other way around.
[SPEAKER_03]: Even the four right efforts, the order that it comes, it says here among
[SPEAKER_03]: So, actually, there's one sutta that he gives like a label to each of his four steps, quote-unquote.
[SPEAKER_03]: The first one is, he prevents unarisen and wholesome states from arising.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's called restraint.
[SPEAKER_03]: Then, he abandons the arisen and wholesome states.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's called dispelling.
[SPEAKER_03]: He gives rise to the unarisen unwholesome states.
[SPEAKER_03]: Wholesome states?
[SPEAKER_03]: Unarisen wholesome states, yes.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's called development.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then, he protects the wholesome states that are already there.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's called, like, protection.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you... it has to be, obviously,
[SPEAKER_03]: It's like a structural thing.
[SPEAKER_03]: You won't... if there is unwholesome there, and you try to cultivate wholesome directly, it's going to be rooted in the same craving to get rid of the thing that was bothering you.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, the wholesomeness can only come when the unwholesomeness is not there anymore.
[SPEAKER_03]: Otherwise, like we said, that's your being.
[SPEAKER_03]: The unwholesomeness is your being.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, any choice that you make is going to be within that unwholesomeness.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, even the choice to fabricate loving-kindness and give all your possessions up or contemplate dhamma, that's going to be done with the unwholesomeness.
[SPEAKER_03]: You can't get rid of something by
[SPEAKER_03]: Covering it up in that manner, you have to... because the problem is always the resistance to the present feeling.
[SPEAKER_03]: So then, if you're doing these things to get rid of the present feeling,
[SPEAKER_03]: Because you think that that's what the dhamma is.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's like, I must get rid of this pressure.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_03]: Even though, externally, quote-unquote, the action looks very wholesome.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because, look, it's the loving-kindness, and it's the renunciation, and it's the contemplation and wisdom that the Buddha talked about.
[SPEAKER_02]: But it's still underlain by the same desire to get rid of pain.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's what makes it wrong.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, like, if someone finds himself, like, with this kind of pressure of wanting to do something, if, like, he cannot just say no but look for something else to do, like, like he feels that kind of a pressure to, I don't know, like...
[SPEAKER_04]: Whatever, like, he wants to do.
[SPEAKER_04]: If you cannot just say no, but want to do something, it will be still rooted in this kind of pressure, whatever it tries to be.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: You can say that way.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, if the mind... if you can't say no to it, then you can see this is an unwholesome pressure.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's something that, if you say no, your mind starts complaining.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's an unwholesome pressure.
[SPEAKER_03]: So...
[SPEAKER_03]: But that, in and of itself, that doesn't mean like...
[SPEAKER_02]: You need to do something about it directly.
[SPEAKER_02]: You need to make sure that you don't act out of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like I said, that's how you don't feed it.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, yeah, the mind might be wanting to do something, but as long as you don't do that, that the mind wants, or anything else that... Like, you would know.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's only something that you can know internally.
[SPEAKER_03]: Which actions would be
[SPEAKER_03]: Going further with this pressure and which actions are kind of neutral.
[SPEAKER_03]: It would totally depend on the present situation.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's not something that you could fix down.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because, like I said, you might have a sensual thought and, okay, going to the park on a certain occasion, for most people, most of the time, you could say that would be an action that won't be proliferating the sensual state further.
[SPEAKER_03]: But
[SPEAKER_03]: Maybe, deep down, you know that when you go to the park, there's going to be, you know, attractive people there, or whatever.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you can't even fix that, because there might be a case where... Now, let's say, this first time you went to the park, it wasn't rooted in sensuality, but then, when you went there, you actually encountered, you know, sensually pleasing things.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, now, the next time, your mind is
[SPEAKER_03]: Going to the park is going to be one of the things that your mind wants to do, on account of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_03]: So now, you can't give in to that.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's always dependent on what is in the present situation.
[SPEAKER_03]: Only you, for yourself, would be able to know, as I already repeated, whether you act it out or not.
[SPEAKER_03]: It always basically requires you to be
[SPEAKER_03]: on guard, because it might sound as if on one level, you know, I'm talking about how people would be too wound up with trying to avoid everything.
[SPEAKER_03]: So then, it might sound like this is a more relaxed approach, which, yes, you kind of relax yourself
[SPEAKER_03]: From doing the stuff that doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_03]: But, on the level that matters, it's actually more strict.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because then, you are forced to... like, if there is that unwholesome state, there's absolutely no justification.
[SPEAKER_03]: There's no extenuating circumstance where you can give in to it and say, oh, but that wasn't unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_03]: No.
[SPEAKER_03]: If you give in, you are acting out of unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_03]: But with a rule, when you take it on the level of external rules and stuff,
[SPEAKER_03]: There can always be exceptions.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, even in the in the vinaya, like, in some situation, if it's like this, or if it's like that, well, then it's not an offense.
[SPEAKER_03]: But with this, it's not.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, if there is the unwholesome state, and you act it out of it, that's it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Nothing else needs to be considered.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: That was an unwholesome intention.
[SPEAKER_01]: That is the more fundamental criteria.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's even what Sutta, I remember, where some monk had difficulty remembering all the rules, and he went to the Buddha,
[SPEAKER_01]: And then the Buddha said, well, do you see wholesome and unwholesome?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then Buddha said, just don't act out of unwholesome by body, speech and mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Can you do that?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, the monk says.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then the sutra ends by saying that monk didn't do anything unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Initially, there was no rules who will basically follow that principle in general.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, and it's... you start off by having these precepts and, you know, on some... you have to start somewhere.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you will be start... starting with the avoidance of
[SPEAKER_03]: Unwholesome states, sorry, of external behaviors, because, practically speaking, if you haven't been keeping the precepts, there will most certainly also be unwholesome pressures making you want to break them, like when you're starting out.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, kind of by accident almost, like without really seeing the level where unwholesome, wholesome and unwholesome is,
[SPEAKER_03]: You would still kind of be withdrawing yourself from it, just by keeping the precepts initially.
[SPEAKER_03]: Then, there will come a point where you... like, keeping the precepts is not painful anymore.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's not really taking you... taking effort.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, then, you need to start looking further and see that now... now, keeping the precepts in and of itself,
[SPEAKER_03]: Because there isn't that pressure anymore to break them.
[SPEAKER_03]: Meaning, the pressure needs to have moved somewhere else now, unless you're an arahant.
[SPEAKER_02]: There must be something else now that your mind is pushing you to do, and you might be justifying it as this is fine, because it's... Look, I'm not breaking any rules.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, so then what would be, like, can we say that
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, at that point, like, you might... And that's actually a point that many monks and people in general, who take on the practice of renunciation, might not go beyond.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like,
[SPEAKER_03]: You know, you might think, oh, because I'm already celibate, I'm already restrained, so there's a...
[SPEAKER_03]: I don't know, the monks are having a meeting at 5 p.m. to drink tea and just chat and socialize.
[SPEAKER_03]: And you would think, well, all of us are, you know, celibate living in this community, we don't talk about unwholesome things, we don't talk about sensuality, but, you know,
[SPEAKER_01]: But you could go there out of the desire to delight in company, for example, which is a more subtle form of unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, then it would be unwholesome, even if everyone is, you know, perfectly well-behaved and stuff.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because there is that pressure, it would be obviously a more subtle form, but it's still the same thing.
[SPEAKER_03]: As the Buddha said, it's even like a little... if you take a... how do you say... with your fingernail, you scoop a little bit of excrement, it smells just as bad as a full bucket.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, even these very subtle things, you can't justify them, because it's...
[SPEAKER_03]: Just by doing that, that would already prevent you from the basic sotāpati.
[SPEAKER_03]: Sotāpati is knowing wholesome is wholesome and unwholesome is unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_03]: So then, by doing these things, you're basically not even trying to look further.
[SPEAKER_03]: By seeing, well, there's more to that principle of wholesome and unwholesome that I'm not seeing.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you would just be believing that because
[SPEAKER_02]: This is kind of a thing that all monks would agree is good or something.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then, it's not bad.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, but that's not really developing the... No, it would be a form of waiting.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, as long as I stay within the boundaries of these precepts, sooner or later, that's gonna happen to me.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, some sort of like a magical waiting for it to come to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, like things, like effacement takes place just on account of keeping the precepts.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That itself would be actually one of the first three fetters that precisely prevents the sotāpanna.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, and speaking about that, that's why it's said in the suttas that the sotāpanna is the one who knows wholesome is wholesome and unwholesome is unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: And in other places it's... And the root of the wholesome.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, the root, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because, in other places also said that, without grasping the sign of the mind, it's impossible for a person to get the right view.
[SPEAKER_02]: And so, then it says, without delighting in seclusion, if they still delight in company, it's impossible that they will get to see the sign of the mind, because it's not like some mystical revelation of an image or perception that comes to you.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's the recognition of those intentions, like the recognition of those impulses, let's call it that way, that are motivating you to do stuff.
[SPEAKER_03]: A sotāpanna is... or a person who... a person gains sotāpatti by being able to see those intentions and then
[SPEAKER_03]: Those background states.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then, that's where you get to see the Four Noble Truths.
[SPEAKER_03]: When the sutta says, he sees as it is.
[SPEAKER_03]: What is suffering?
[SPEAKER_03]: What is the origin of suffering?
[SPEAKER_03]: What is the cessation of suffering?
[SPEAKER_03]: Where is the path leading to the cessation of suffering?
[SPEAKER_03]: As it is doesn't mean, like, sometimes it would get translated as it truly is, or as it really is.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, you get some sort of hidden revelation.
[SPEAKER_03]: But no, it just means you had these intentions there, and when you were contemplating,
[SPEAKER_03]: What suffering was, or what craving was, it was always kind of over there.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, you weren't seeing this stuff while it was there.
[SPEAKER_03]: This this kind of background mental attitudes.
[SPEAKER_03]: You were not seeing craving on that level.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's the only place where it can be seen.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_03]: So then, you were thinking, oh, the craving is like... Like I said, you started like that.
[SPEAKER_03]: You would have started by thinking, oh, craving is when I go out and do these things.
[SPEAKER_03]: But no.
[SPEAKER_03]: Craving is that background attitude of the mind.
[SPEAKER_03]: So,
[SPEAKER_03]: Recognizing that background attitude of the mind is seeing the sign of the mind.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's why that's indispensable.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, literally, you absolutely cannot become a sotāpanna without seeing that.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because anything that you think craving is, won't be craving.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because it will be basically, like, secondary.
[SPEAKER_03]: You might be able to see... What most people are seeing, usually, is the... when they think of craving, it's, like, already further
[SPEAKER_03]: It's down the line of where those attitudes come.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, they might think of all these thoughts and these agitation that I experienced, and then they might get rid of it by doing a relaxation meditation technique.
[SPEAKER_03]: But all of that arose in the first place, because you didn't see the background attitude of your mind.
[SPEAKER_03]: You acted out of it, and that led to all this particular disturbance coming up.
[SPEAKER_03]: But if you had seen that from the very start, then nothing... like, you wouldn't be able to overlook, even if you wanted to, that acting out of this is not for your benefit.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because it's like, who on earth would think that, like, if you let a child
[SPEAKER_03]: That's already spoiled and it's throwing a tantrum.
[SPEAKER_03]: Who on earth would think that just letting it keep going that direction is going to result in something good?
[SPEAKER_03]: It just becomes immediately apparent that, no, that there is no benefit that can come from me giving in to this.
[SPEAKER_03]: So then, that's why the Buddha said, if you see one noble truth, you see all of them.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because it's all about seeing... all of it just becomes apparent when you see, oh,
[SPEAKER_03]: What am I actually doing here?
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, am I trying to get rid of pleasure?
[SPEAKER_03]: Am I trying...
[SPEAKER_03]: Sorry, am I trying to get more pleasure?
[SPEAKER_03]: Am I trying to get rid of pain?
[SPEAKER_03]: On that background level, anyone can think that they already see that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, I know when I'm lustful or angry, but if you're not a sotāpanna, it's because there's still more depth to that recognition of what it even means to try to get rid of pain or go for pleasure.
[SPEAKER_04]: Can we, like, ask, like, because you were saying, like, seeing the sign of the mind is, like, a necessary thing in order to recognize what's wholesome, what's unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_04]: Then you say, like, seclusion is, like, a necessary basis to see the sign of the mind.
[SPEAKER_04]: Can we say, can we clarify, like, why, like, not being into seclusion, like, obstruct us from seeing the sign of the mind?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, well, the the most obvious thing that comes to mind is when you live with a... when you're overly involved with other people.
[SPEAKER_03]: What automatically happens is, whether you recognize it or not, like, that's what, you know, peer pressure and stuff.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, you regard, you would start to be regarding as good, or as, or as, like, what should be done.
[SPEAKER_03]: You would take it on the level of what these other people are doing.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, it's just a natural kind of human thing, that you measure yourself by what, what people in your environment do.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, that's on the most obvious level.
[SPEAKER_03]: But, as well, the, the...
[SPEAKER_03]: The kind of problem with being... with delighting in company is that... that requires you to overlook that background attitude.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, the fact that you're delighting in company, in and of itself, already means that you're overlooking the background attitude.
[SPEAKER_01]: You are pretending or delighting in something which moves in the other direction.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you're already, like, trying to look away.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, there's the only way that you can delight in company is because you want to kind of...
[SPEAKER_03]: Get out of this container that is your experience.
[SPEAKER_03]: You want, like, to get out into this other thing out there or other people out there that will, sort of, give you some kind of ease.
[SPEAKER_03]: The same way as you might, you know, drink or you're kind of seeking this external to forget about this situation.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or call someone because you feel lonely or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so, just, you know, by talking,
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the word, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: You kind of release the... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whereas, actually, you can't.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just as... that is the same as giving in to the child's tantrum.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, one needs to then recognize that, yeah, like, you know, and then... but you see, this is... because mind can play tricks.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, no, I'm just calling someone to see how they're doing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, well, sure, that might be there, but there's something even more fundamental going on there.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when... so, this has to come with the basic sense of honesty.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And this is the whole authenticity, basically, the discussion feeds into this as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you can't be saved by someone else.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: And even by your own mind, like, you need to have an attitude of almost perpetual suspicion.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, you can't, you can't trust that, because your mind is telling you that my motivation is such and such.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not your ally, that mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, but you see, but then that's the thing, because if somebody has established, let's say, that sense of suspicion, that is, right here and now, the birth of sati, of, like,
[SPEAKER_01]: recollection, or mindfulness as it is properly translated.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, rather than signing up to a 10-day group retreat, or a 20-day group retreat, or whatever group retreat, where one assumes I'm going to learn a method and I'm going to gradually become more mindful and aware, that's actually never going to happen.
[SPEAKER_01]: The moment you assume that you can gradually become mindful and aware, you are already overlooking
[SPEAKER_01]: The intention that, right now, you're giving yourself time in order to gradually go there.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, whereas what you want to see is that you have no choice but to act right here and now.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if you see that you cannot fully trust your mind, but at the same time that you can develop that mind, then it is that attitude of suspiciousness which you just coined it, that is what will give rise to the full-blown mindfulness on the spot.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if somebody has understood just that,
[SPEAKER_01]: For the rest of their life, they never need to go to any group meditation retreat again in order to learn how to be mindful.
[SPEAKER_01]: If that attitude is right, they will see the consequences of this.
[SPEAKER_01]: You will have freed yourself from this whole religious spiritual circus of accumulating this, that and the other, in order to gradually gain what you think is wholesome,
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's never gonna happen.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, but the problem is, see, that comes with a burden now, because when you go to the retreat or wherever it might be, like, it might be difficult in the external sense, like, oh, you have to sit for 15 hours a day or whatever, but nothing.
[SPEAKER_03]: Even the torture, literal physical torture, like the ascetics back in the Buddha's day, they could sleep on beds made of nails and stuff.
[SPEAKER_03]: But nothing is more unpleasant, in that kind of deeply unsettling sense, than questioning
[SPEAKER_03]: your own mind.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, not going with the grain, when it's that tantrum is there, and not going with it.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's the most unpleasant thing.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you would free yourself from the external duty of, you know, following these practices and stuff, but
[SPEAKER_03]: At the expense of, right now, like we mentioned before, most people want to be free from suffering ASAP.
[SPEAKER_03]: They're not willing to accept the fact that, you know, the recognition of what's wholesome might initially be unpleasant, because the mind doesn't value that direction.
[SPEAKER_03]: But, see, that would free you, but that's not... it doesn't come for free, and it certainly doesn't go
[SPEAKER_03]: In the same direction that you're used to.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you're gonna have to kind of break.
[SPEAKER_03]: And when you break, there's always that, you know.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: And it leaves you very much like, you know, on your own in it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you're fully responsible and that can be overwhelming as well for people.
[SPEAKER_03]: To the extent that you were depending on external safety,
[SPEAKER_03]: This is going to feel unpleasant, because it kind of suddenly, like, sweeps the floor that you were sitting on, sweeps it out.
[SPEAKER_01]: Pulls the rug, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, it's not going to stay unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, of course.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, someone needs to understand that it might be, let's say, somewhat of a bitter pill to swallow in the beginning, but when the... when that sort of right effort is put in, then it's not going to stay unpleasant like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: On the contrary, that is where it's going to be... that independence from external circumstances becomes the foundation of the true freedom then.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's how it ties in with the authenticity.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's why authenticity is indispensable for any progress in dhamma, because if you are not willing to always question your mental states, and question that it doesn't matter how right it feels,
[SPEAKER_03]: For you to be doing X, Y or Z, there still might be greed, aversion and delusion in it.
[SPEAKER_03]: If you're not willing to take that on, then... which is what authenticity is, then you will be justifying non-dhamma as dhamma.
[SPEAKER_03]: You will be justifying greed, aversion and delusion as non-greed, non-aversion and non-delusion.
[SPEAKER_03]: Or at least, certainly, you will not know it
[SPEAKER_03]: For sure, for what it is.
[SPEAKER_03]: You might, as it's said in the Sutta, you might, like, I don't do anything bad.
[SPEAKER_03]: But, as the Buddha defined, that's not... because the baby also doesn't do anything bad.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, that, that in and of itself, that's not it.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's not it.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, only with that authenticity, you become able to, eh... recognize, again, these, these, eh...
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, you can at least have the openness to question yourself.
[SPEAKER_03]: It doesn't mean that you will see things immediately, but you will at least be having, again, that suspiciousness that I mentioned.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, whatever you think is wholesome, you don't take it for granted, because
[SPEAKER_03]: If you know what is wholesome, you should be free from suffering right now.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: Not like I know what's wholesome and then somehow later on that gives me some result.
[SPEAKER_03]: Knowing what's wholesome frees you from suffering.
[SPEAKER_03]: In the same way, knowing the escape from suffering frees you from suffering.
[SPEAKER_03]: Not like, I know the escape, then I do something, and then I get the escape.
[SPEAKER_02]: Understanding wholesomeness, like right view, really, is where the freedom is.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not right knowledge leads to right liberation.